So I want to give people first a chance
to practice the props approach, and then
I'll reset the context in terms of the lead-in
into the next technique that I think
is really important when it comes to the model of web
development and how we look at things.
We did get a great question here in the chat.
And so it's this around the idea of when
in a lot of real-world apps, a lot of times
you're getting large sets of data from your API.
And so in the case of the question is user details.
And so if you're creating a component like user card,
how might you approach this?
So again, just for the sake of not just me talking,
let's at least scaffold this out a little bit,
just so there's something visual for us to have.
Let's go to the playground.
And then we'll go into our app.
OK, there we go.
And so what I'm going to do here, I'm
going to create a file called usercard.dashView.
And then let me just do this real quick to set up the scaffold.
Let's keep it easy.
User.
All right, so we have a user card component.
And then I'll explain what is the question here.
User card from components.usercard.view, user card, OK.
And then here, we have a user card like that.
So let me run up.
Wait, wrong thing to run devin.
All right, cool.
This is too small, so we're going to bump that, bump that,
bump that, close that.
OK, so the question here is around
this concept of what happens when you get a large data object.
So inside of here, for instance, let's just
define it here real quick, is that let's
say we have a user data object that we end up fetching
from the API that has something like name, then preferred
framework, view, for example, favorite food, sushi,
and then let's just keep it.
OK, so let's say it's like this level of object,
or actually, let's go ahead and, what's one more thing?
Let's just say, I don't know, favorite numbers.
This can be an array, and that can be like eight, what, 10.
These are not actually my favorite numbers,
but for the sake of the exercise, OK.
We have this complex thing.
And so the question here is, if the user card, for example,
let's say on the user card, we only
want to display a couple of things.
We want to display the name.
We want to display the, what else do we got?
We got name.
And let's just say favorite food.
Let's actually just say two things.
And so if we refresh this, they're very good.
OK, the question here is around data architecture,
and how do we actually manage this?
Because there's one way we can do this, right?
Let's talk about the first approach.
Probably the most straightforward approach
is to just say that, hey, inside of this component,
I'm going to take this prop called user,
and it's going to be a type of object,
and I'm going to require it.
And then here is where I'll say user.name
and user.favoritefood, because that corresponds with this data
that we're going to go ahead and pass here directly,
user equals user data.
So if we take a look at how that looks here,
whoop, didn't I save?
There we go.
You see user bin appears, and sushi appears.
OK, so it's working.
But the question here is, as you'll notice,
is that we have passed in more data than we actually need.
And so I think the question is kind of like,
what's the right way?
And like a lot of programming things,
there is no singular right way.
A lot of times what it ends up boiling down to when
it comes to managing this stuff is the complexity
around maintenance of the component.
That's what I would basically say.
There are certainly sometimes concerns
that, oh, the data you're passing in is so massive
that it doesn't make sense to pass to that single component.
But then I would argue at that point,
the bottleneck is not the component architecture,
but maybe how data is being fetched and being parsed
on the higher level.
This is why I think stuff like GraphQL
has gotten really popular, because if the servers are just
returning giant blobs of data, that's
expensive for the user.
There's no amount of smart things
you can do as far as like, if you're just
getting more data than you need from your server,
that's a problem that has to be dealt at that end
and not necessarily at this level.
And so in this case, however, though,
let's say this was a lot bigger.
Let's just say this was a lot bigger, right?
And you're like, I really don't want to pass that.
There honestly is nothing wrong just being like, well,
that we'll have a name.
It'll be string.
And this time we'll just say it's a default of John Doe.
And then we'll also have a food prop that is a type string.
And we'll default it to cheeseburgers, right?
And so it's cool about this now with the default,
because this is, I think the first time I'm demoing this,
is that if in the event we don't include anything on the app
side, you'll see, what did I break?
You used user in here?
Oh, I did.
You're totally right.
Good catch is no longer an object.
It's just individual properties.
There you go.
User favorite food.
Yes, this is just food.
OK, you can see we have John Doe and cheeseburgers.
And then as a result, what you get
is now, OK, let's just say Ben's favorite food is cheeseburger.
Well, then in that case, userdata.name
can be the only thing that we pass.
And you'll notice that Ben is good default prop
stays cheeseburger.
And then here, you can also then say, you know what?
Then also for favorite food, then be userdata.favoritefood.
And then it still works.
And so again, it's one of those things
I think with experience, you'll come to figure out like one,
when is it too many props?
Because I will say that is actually a legitimate problem.
If you have the point where you're breaking down your object
and you have like 10 lines of props,
no one's going to want to read that.
No one wants to deal with that.
But again, feel it out with your team.
Figure out like, what is your limit?
For me, once I start getting past like three to five props,
I start wondering if I could maybe manipulate the data just
past like a concise object that can then
be spread out inside of the component.
But again, it's one of those things
where you'll have a style as far as how you approach that.
Yeah.
But that would be where you might use a computed property
to pass as a prop?
I love it.
OK.
So the question here is that then with this same concept,
right, could we then use a computed property
to pass it down instead?
And I think that's a great example.
So once again, let's take this example.
If we want to say only pass down the food and the name,
we could say, call it refined user data.
And this refined user data can basically just
be like returns an object where we do, what is it, name,
and then just this.userdata.name, and then food.
This.userdata.favorite.
Food.
And that way, you actually get to massage the data
a little bit anyways.
And then we can revert back to this user
now, which can just be passed.
And it'll be pass refined user data.
And so it means we'll update this now to be user type object
required true.
And this time, we can then say user.name.
Actually, I could have just done that like that.
There we go.
What did I break?
Cannot read properties defined, name, computed, return, name.
Oh, OK.
It did work.
I just didn't save app.vue.
OK.
So there you go.
That's an example of passing down just the data you need
into your component so that it doesn't have to deal with the
crux of all the other data properties.
And so once again, it'll be a stylistic part as far as
feeling out what makes the most sense in terms of is that
level of complexity even needed?
Because if it's just one or two extra properties, I'd say
most of the time, it's not worth creating an entirely
separate property just to refine the data a little bit.
Granted, if you have a massive card that has a ton of
stuff in it, then that's the point where once again, whether
using things like serverless functions, for example, those
are great ways to massage the data so that when they come
back from the back end, it's smaller in the way that you
want.
That's one approach to that as well.
Because for example here, one of the APIs we have to play
with later in the workshop is if you take a look at
something like this, this is actually a great example of a
really complicated copy, paste.
This is the entire thing for the Pokemon Ditto.
And there's a lot of stuff in here that you
probably don't need.
You probably need one image.
You need maybe the number it is, and you
maybe need to render.
But this is an example of a lot of raw data that you don't
necessarily need.
And so once again, there are different approaches to handle
this, but I hope that answers that question.
So thank you for asking that.
Cool.
All right.
Yes?
Is when you do pass properties, is it sort of passing by a
reference, or is it passing a copy of the object?
Just because we're talking about performance and memory.
OK.
So the question here is that when you pass in this refined
user data, is it passing in a copy of it, or is it passing a
reference to that data?
And the answer is that it's passing a
reference to that data.
And so when it comes to props, that actually does bring up
the concept of mutating props.
Generally speaking, not a good practice.
So what you don't want to do is come in here and then be like,
oh yes, I want, I'm going to create a method that's like
change name, and it'll be like this.user.name equals
like Charlie.
Like, you don't want to do this.
But you could.
But as you can see, though, unexpected mutation of
user prop is yelling at you.
Because once again, when you start muddling up the chain
of command as far as how data flows, it starts to get
really tricky to figure out what's happening now.
Now again, this leads into the question that we had earlier
regarding, well, if that's the case, are you saying that
my child component can't change the data it's happening?
No, that's not the case at all.
But before we move on to that topic, does anyone have any
other questions about the exercise they've worked with
in terms of props, that kind of stuff?
If the data changes outside the component since it's passed
by reference, will it re-render the component then?
Yeah, it'll know basically what parts of the DOM to update
and all the dependencies.
So that's one of the advantages is that basically all the
reactivity view tracks and takes care of.